Start with a right triangle that has legs of
length a and b and a hypotenuse of length c.
Rotate and shift a copy of this
triangle so that they align
like this, and notice that the two connected
angles are complementary by construction.
We can add this line to make a trapezoid, and
the interior triangle here is right-angled by
construction. Let's compute the area of the
resulting trapezoid, called Garfield's trapezoid,
in two different ways. First of all, the
area of the trapezoid is the product of
the average of the two bases with the height.
So the area is a plus b over 2 times a plus b,
which expands to a squared
plus 2ab plus b squared over 2.
Alternatively, the trapezoid
is built from three triangles,
so its area is the sum of the
areas of those three triangles.
The first two triangles in this sum
are congruent and have the same area of
one-half times a times b or a times b over 2.
The last triangle has area one-half times c
squared so that the area of the trapezoid
is 2 times a times b plus c squared over 2.
But this means that a squared plus 2ab
plus b squared over 2 is equal to 2 times a
times b plus c squared over 2. Multiplying this
equality by 2 and subtracting 2 times a times b
results in a squared plus b squared is equal
to c squared. This is the Pythagorean theorem.